Guide to the Maxwell E. Foster Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maxwell E. Foster papers
1809-1982
1850-1923
YCAL MSS 662
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.63
(8 boxes)
The papers consist of letters to Foster and material relating to the Parkman, Twisleton, and Vaughan families. Correspondents include James Latimer McLane, Jr., Charlton MacVeagh, Ellery Sedgwick, Anne Shiras, and others. Material relating to the Parkman, Twisleton, and Vaughan families include correspondence, financial and legal records, documents, and notebooks.
Foster, Maxwell E., 1901-1983
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired primarily through purchase from Serendipity Books on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2000. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Maxwell E. Foster (1901-1983)
Maxwell E. Foster was born 27 August 1901 in Manchester, Massachusetts to Reginald and Harriet (Lawrence) Foster. He was raised in Boston and educated at Groton, Yale University (1923), and Harvard Law School (1926). After passing the bar, Foster joined the Boston firm of Choate, Hall & Stewart, later becoming a partner in the firm. In 1942, he joined the Office of Price Administration (OPA) and later transferred to the Board of Economic Welfare. Later in life, he devoted himself to research in languages and literature. His literary publications include the posthumous The Play Behind the Play: Hamlet and Quarto One (1991).
Biographical information taken from printed obituary in collection.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of letters to Maxwell E. Foster and material relating to the Parkman, Twisleton, and Vaughan families. Correspondents include James Latimer McLane, Jr., Charlton MacVeagh, Ellery Sedgwick, Anne Shiras, and others. Materials relating to the Parkman, Twisleton, and Vaughan families include correspondence, financial and legal records, documents, and notebooks.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings by date of acquisition: May 2000 Acquisition, July 2000 Acquisition, September 2003 Acquisition, and August 2005 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Foster, Maxwell E., 1901-1983; McLane, James Latimer, 1898-; MacVeagh, Charlton, 1901-; Sedgwick, Ellery, 1872-1960; Shiras, Anne; Parkman family; Twisleton family; Vaughan family
- May 2000 Acquisition, 1918-1982; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  May 2000 Acquisition consists of letters to Foster from James Latimer McLane, Jr., Charlie MacVeagh, Jr., Charlton MacVeagh, Ellery Sedgwick and others, with the bulk of the letters dating from his undergraduate years at Yale University. Includes one letter from Foster to Charlton MacVeagh.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 89.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund.
  - Foster, [Harriet (Lawrence)?], undated (Box 1)
  - McLane, James Latimer, 1918-1922, undated; 23 (Box 1)
  - MacVeagh, Charlie, 1919 November 12 (Box 1)
  - MacVeagh, Charlton, 1919-1923, undated; 23 (Box 1)
  - Sedgwick, Ellery; Sedgwick, Shawn, 1919-1920, undated (Box 2)
  - First name only, undated (Box 2)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1919-1982, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - Printed ephemera, 1926, 1957 (Box 2)
- July 2000 Acquisition, 1809-1925; 6; (6 boxes)
  July 2000 Acquisition consists of papers relating to the Parkman, Twisleton, and Vaughan families. The papers, dating chiefly from the 19th century, include correspondence, writings, financial records, photographs, and other material.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 61.
  - Twisleton, Parkman, and Vaughan Family Papers
    - Abbot, Myra [Margaret], 1809-1813 (Box 3)
    - Agassiz, Elizabeth, 1898 (Box 3)
    - Benjamin, S. S., 1874 (Box 3)
    - Bliss, E. A., undated (Box 3)
    - Bowditch, H., undated (Box 3)
    - Bruen, Mary, undated (Box 3)
    - Bullard, Louisa A., 1851 (Box 3)
    - Cabot, Bunny Elizabeth Dwight, [circa 1840-1859]; 2 (Box 3)
    - Carlyle, Jane, undated (Box 3)
    - Coolidge, Sally T., 1868, undated (Box 3)
    - "Cora", undated (Box 3)
    - [Curran, M.?], 1848 (Box 3)
    - Curtis, Mary F., 1848 (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Chapman, 1863 (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Edmund, 1815-1847 (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Edward [Thug Boy], 1847-1862 (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Elizabeth and Mary, undated (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Mary E., 1846-1848 (Box 3)
    - Dwight, D., undated (Box 3)
    - Dwight, Mary and Edmund, 1823-1857, undated (Box 3)
    - Eliot, E. L. and Mary, undated (Box 3)
    - Eliot, Samuel A., 1857 (Box 3)
    - Ellis, Ms., 1862 (Box 3)
    - Emerson, George B., Lucy and R. W., 1848-1859, undated (Box 3)
    - Ford, Richard, [1854] (Box 3)
    - [French and Spanish letters], 1855 (Box 3)
    - Gardiner, Mary C., undated (Box 3)
    - Gisborne, Emily, undated (Box 3)
    - Green [in Rome], 1859 (Box 3)
    - Guild, Eliza, Harriet, S. Eliot and Mary S., undated (Box 3)
    - Hale, George S. and E. P., undated (Box 3)
    - Henson, Madeline, 1858 (Box 3)
    - Howard, Lissie B., 1850 (Box 3)
    - Jackson, Maria and Marianne, undated (Box 3)
    - Leigh, Ms. and Caroline, undated (Box 3)
    - "Lilly", 1859 (Box 3)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1894 (Box 3)
    - Loring, William Caleb, Mary, and Jane L., undated (Box 3)
    - Lowndes, Sarah B., 1831 (Box 3)
    - MacIntosh, Mary, undated (Box 3)
    - Mills, Anna, Arthur, Charles, Achilles, 1841-1849, undated; 2 (Box 3)
    - Minot, Kate and William, [circa 1890] (Box 3)
    - Morrison, Samuel Eliot, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Norton, Catherine E., undated (Box 3)
    - Parker, Emily, 1862 (Box 3)
    - Parkman, Mary E., [circa 1850-1899]; 10 (Box 3)
    - Parkman family, [circa 1894-1899, undated]; 6 (Box 4)
    - Perkins, Fanny, undated (Box 4)
    - Perkins, Mary, undated (Box 4)
    - "Sally", 1849 (Box 4)
    - "Sarah" [Sarah Parkman Coolidge?], 1855-1860 (Box 4)
    - "Saye and Sele", 1854 (Box 4)
    - Sedgwick, E. B. and Charles, 1831 (Box 4)
    - Shaw, Mary L., undated (Box 4)
    - "Shelton", 1842 (Box 4)
    - Sturgis, Sue, undated (Box 4)
    - Thayer, Caroline C., 1850 (Box 4)
    - Thomas, Lucinda O., undated (Box 4)
    - Ticknor, Anna E., undated (Box 4)
    - Ticknor, George, 1857, undated (Box 4)
    - Tilton, Mrs. Abram, undated (Box 4)
    - Trowbridge, H. S., undated (Box 4)
    - Twisleton, Caroline, undated (Box 4)
    - Twisleton, Edward, undated (Box 4)
    - Twisleton, Edward Turner Boyd, 1855 (Box 4)
    - Twisleton, Ellen Dwight, 1858-1860, undated; 4 (Box 4)
    - Vaughan, S., 1836 (Box 4)
    - Vaughan family, [circa 1870-1925]; 3 (Box 4)
    - Wadsworth, E. A., 1850 (Box 4)
    - Ware, John, 1851 (Box 4)
    - Unsorted correspondence, manuscripts, notes, bills, and receipts, [circa 1857-1903]; 5 (Box 4)
    - Diary, 1862 (Box 4)
    - Vaughan family: unsorted correspondence, [circa 1888-1907]; 14 (Box 5)
    - Vaughan family: unsorted correspondence, [circa 1866-1924]; 18 (Box 6)
    - Vaughan family: unsorted correspondence, [circa 1886-1907]; 16 (Box 7)
    - Vaughan family: unsorted correspondence, [circa 1886-1907]; 14 (Box 8)
- September 2003 Acquisition, 1928 October 16
  September 2003 Acquisition consists of a single typed letter signed to Foster from Anne Shiras.
  Former call number: Uncat Za File 674.
  Gift of Peter B. Howard and Matt Needle.
  - Shiras, Anne, 1928 October 16 (Box 8)
- August 2005 Acquisition, undated
  August 2005 Acquisition consists of two autograph letters signed from Jane Carlyle to Mrs. Parkman.
  Former call number: Uncat Za File 700.
  Gift of Peter B. Howard.
  - Carlyle, Jane to Mrs. Parkman, undated (Box 8)